<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter vvritten by those of the assembly in Rochell: to Monsieur le Duc de Les Diguieres Containing an admonition vnto him, to leaue the enemie, and to ayde them. As also an exhortation and a warning vnto those that forsake the trueth, and cleaue vnto the enemies thereof, to shun that vengeance which God will send downe vpon them for the same.</title>
            <title>Lettre de Messieurs l'Assemblee, a Monsieur le duc de Lesdiguieres. English</title>
            <author>Eglises réformées de France. Assemblée générale (1620-1621 : La Rochelle)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105630</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841357</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841357</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5934</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01189)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5934)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1202:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter vvritten by those of the assembly in Rochell: to Monsieur le Duc de Les Diguieres Containing an admonition vnto him, to leaue the enemie, and to ayde them. As also an exhortation and a warning vnto those that forsake the trueth, and cleaue vnto the enemies thereof, to shun that vengeance which God will send downe vpon them for the same.</title>
                  <title>Lettre de Messieurs l'Assemblee, a Monsieur le duc de Lesdiguieres. English</title>
                  <author>Eglises réformées de France. Assemblée générale (1620-1621 : La Rochelle)</author>
                  <author>Lesdiguiéres, François de Bonne, duc de, 1543-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Edward Allde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed in Rochell [i.e. London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the 12. of Iuly. 1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Bessay. President. Rossell. Lieutenant. Guerin. Secretarie. de la Porte. Secretarie.</note>
                  <note>A translation of; Lettre de Messieurs l'Assemblee, a Monsieur le duc de Lesdiguieres.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; printed at London by Edward Allde (STC).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eglises réformées de France --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Huguenots --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5934:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5934:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER VVRITTEN BY THOSE of the Aſſembly in ROCHELL: To Monſieur <hi>le Duc de LES DIGVIERES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing an admonition vnto him, to leaue the Enemie, and to ayde them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo an exhortation and a warning vnto thoſe that forſake the trueth, and</hi> cleaue vnto the Enemies thereof, to ſhun that vengeance which God will ſend <hi>downe vpon them for the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in Rochell the 12. of Iuly. 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:5934:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5934:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER VVRIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEN BY THOSE OF <hi>the Aſſemblie in Rochell: To Monſieur le Duc de</hi> LES DIGVIERES.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MONSIEVR.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the pittifull eſtate whereinto our Enemies haue reduced the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of this Realme, it would be a great comfort and conſolation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, if wee were but to fight and contend againſt falſe accuſations, and to defend our ſelues againſt the violent Counſels and courſes of thoſe, who openly adhearing vnto Antichriſtian Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie, eſteeming it a title of Honour to be call'd our Enemies, for hauing ſufficiently ſatisfied the firſt by our moſt humble Supplications and atteſtations to his Maieſtie, and by our declaration newly publiſhed, wee hope that God will bleſſe and proſper our iuſt defence, and preſerue his Churches from the vtter ruine, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are threatned. But wee cannot sufficiently
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5934:3"/>expreſſe, with what griefe of heart wee feele and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our ſelues bound to maintaine our Innocencie againſt thoſe, who as well as wee, haue part in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick intereſts of our Churches: ſpecially vnto your ſelfe my Lord, whoſe age, experience, and offices, make your proceedings more dangerous and hurtfull vnto thoſe againſt whom you employ them. We haue heretofore laboured therein, by the Letters that haue beene deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vnto you, from vs, and perceiuing the ſmall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit that wee haue thereby receiued, wee had reſolued with our ſelues to reſt ſilent, if our conſciences did not binde and pricke forward vs, to ſtirre vp and quicken yours, by ſetting before your eyes the great hurt and detriment that you bring to the Church of God, at ſuch a time, wherein it hath moſt neede of your ayde and aſſiſtance. It was not without good reaſon, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience it ſelfe ſheweth vs, that the laſt aſſembly at Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dun, doubted of the accompliſhment of the promiſes that were made vnto vs, at the Court: But your word interpoſing it ſelfe, with that of <hi>Monſieur de Chaſtillion,</hi> together with the conſideration of the ſtate wherein you were, made vs reſolue vpon a new proofe, aſſiſting our ſelues, that the effect of the words giuen vnto vs, failing, you would make yours effectuall, for the ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly, which in that caſe was to re-aſſemble, and cauſe them to obtaine that iuſt proceeding that had beene promiſed vnto them. With what diſpleaſure our Churches that ſent vs hether, haue beene tormented, when they perceiue that you diſapproue it, that you blame it, and that by your Letters, you preferre the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours and pretences of the perſecution, at this day raiſed againſt faithfull Innocents, before the preiudice of our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5934:3"/>cauſe? The ſtate wherein you were in, the precedent voyage that you made to the Court, made honeſt men apprehend, that if after you withdrew your ſelfe from the Court, you returned thether againe, you ſhould be bound to effect ſome preiudiciall action, againſt the Church of God, and therefore they deſired you, to ſtand ſtill in your gouernment during the ſubſiſtance of this aſſembly. But without any reſpect or regard co the requeſts and intreaties of ſo many Churches, you left your Prouince, made another voyage to the Court, and for the contentment of our Enemies, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of thoſe of our profeſſion, by your preſence you authoriſe thoſe that inceſſantly labour to worke our ruine and deſtruction. Your proteſtation to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the ſame profeſſion, the refuſall of the dignity, that was offered vnto you, vpon condition to change your Religion, and your reconciliation not long ſince made vnto the Church at Charenton, put vs in good comfort, and made vs hope of ſome good effect for the good and benefit of our affaires, and ſome happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the paines that you ſhould take therein. But our Enemies haue gotten this aduantage, that your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample hauing been made more conſiderable, the blame which you impoſe vpon this aſſembly, is more notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and your diſunion with our aſſembly, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth all the Churches of this Realme, is more do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mageable, ſeruing for a pretence vnto thoſe, (who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hope by that meanes to keepe themſelues cloſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of this publike calamity,) to ſeperate themſelues from our Vnion, from the which; thoſe that haue deſigned our deſtruction, ſeeke to diſunite the Prouinces, Churches, and perſons of greateſt quality,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5934:4"/>therein vſing your name and authority, for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo pernicious a deſigne; pernicious certainely we may well ſay: for to what end thinke you, my Lord, ſuch proceedings may tend but onely to weaken vs, and make our deſtruction more eaſie, and leſſe hazard vnto thoſe that vndertake it? <hi>Monſieur de Pleſsis,</hi> who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect of that, that had happened to <hi>Nauarreux,</hi> and after throughout all the Country of Bearn, being carried away by your Counſell, and abuſed by the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular promiſes that were made vnto him, at this day feeleth the effects of this proceeding. In your preſence beholding the Towne of Saumur taken from him, and put into anothers mans hands. The Inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of making profeſſion of the ſame Religion, ſubiected to a Papiſticall Garriſon: The Vniuerſitie which he with ſo much paines and great care had there erected, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. The Church in the ſame place made deſtitute of her firſt liberty, and all thoſe of this Realme depriued of the ſafety and ſecurity that they had in that place. Hath not the like dealing beene vſed vnto the reſt of the Gouernours of the places that wee had for ſecurity in Poictow, ſeeing that in ſtead of commaund in them, as they did for the ſecurity of our Churches, they are now commaunded by Garriſons of a contrary Religion, to the ruine and ſubuerſion of the Flockes of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt? Doe theſe proceedings, that followed the ſedition in Towers, and were accompanied with the taking of Iargeau, and the violent diſarmings of thoſe of the Religion in diuers places, and ſeconded with the beſieging of Saint Iohn Angely, at this time furiouſly battered, beare any ſhew of any good intent that is meant towards vs to doe vs iuſtice? But are they not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5934:4"/>directly contrary to the declarations not long ſince publiſhed, and to the particular promiſes made in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of thoſe that would addict themſelues vnto that which the Court deſireth of them? and doc they not make euery man manifeſtly and plainely ſee, that the obedience whereof they ſo highly cry out, and which is required of vs, by demaunding pardon and abſolution, and that wee ſhould ſeperate our aſſemblie, before wee haue iuſtice done vnto vs, or any ſecurity for our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, tendeth onely, to bind vs to lay our throats open vnto thoſe, that haue an intent and deſire to our them? What faults are we culpable of, being aſſembled vpon the permiſſion that had beene graunted and giuen vnto vs, by thoſe words that to vs ſhould be as good an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance as Letters Patents, yea and vpon yours alſo? What fault haue we committed, that being aſſembled, haue ſought by all ſubmiſſiue meanes poſſible vnto his Maieſtie, to obtaine that iuſtice that had beene promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto vs, when wee remitted the purſuite thereof to our generall Deputies, and deſired thoſe that are of the greateſt quality and degrees, and make profeſſion of the Religion in this Realme, to ioyne their interceſſions with them? And ſeeing that in ſtead of finding the effect of the performance of the promiſes made vnto vs, vpon your iuſt and moſt humble ſupplications preſented vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Maieſtie: we haue beene proclaimed Rebels, and declared to be criminals; and that as ſuch, our proceſſe hath beene made, ſome of vs haue beene executed by pictures, ſeeing in Viuards they haue riſen vp in Armes, beſieged, battered, and taken thoſe place's that we held, and in them, contrary to the agreements made, murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome, and vſed great violences vnto vs, that at this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5934:5"/>preſent they beſiege, and furiouſly batter the Towne of S. Iohn D'angely: can men iuſtly blame vs, if againſt ſuch violences wee oppoſe our defence, which nature teacheth euery man, and the law of God neuer reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth?</p>
            <p>In the meane time, God forbid, that this extremitie whereinto we are reduced by conſtraint, ſhould in our hearts deface that moſt humble obedience, and moſt faithfull ſeruice that wee owe vnto our King, wherein wee proteſt inuiolably to continue, deſiring nothing more, nor ſo much then, that in the iuſtice and ſecurity required by vs for our Churches, wee may attaine the meanes of a good and an aſſured peace in this ſtate, which as much as in vs lyeth we haue, &amp; to our powers doe ſeek for: beſeeching God with all our hearts, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and preſerue the King, from thoſe dangers which the Enemies of his ſtate, expoſe his perſon vnto, in the perils of warre. In the meane time, my Lord, the iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our cauſe, which ſo manifeſtly appeareth, and which God will alwayes make to ſhine, as bright as the Sunne at noone time, doth not hinder you, by your preſence, from approuing the proceedings, that are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt vs; and which is more, blotting out the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the griefes that our Churches receiue, you promiſe and procure fauour vnto thoſe, who lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs, will ioyne themſelues vnto our Enemies, as you ſolicite them, by that meanes putting into the mouth of the Church at this day, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint that the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> made, ſaying, That his neereſt friends, behaued themſelues diſloyally towards him, &amp; were become his Enemies. The Sauiour of the world teacheth vs, that a houſe deuided in it ſelfe cannot ſtand. Iudge then my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5934:5"/>Lord, if it pleaſe you, what puniſhment they incurre that ſhall haue beene a meanes to ſtirre vp deuiſion in the houſe of God, and whether God will not reuenge the deſtruction thereof, not only vpon thoſe that open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly procure it, but alſo on thoſe that in any manner or by any meanes ſhall haue contributed vnto the ſame. But after we had ſeene what hath beene done in Bearn, Viuarez, and againſt the aſſembly, after that by your preſence you haue fauoured a puiſſant Armie againſt the Churches of this Realme, and the loſſe of many places, that had beene giuen vs to hold for our ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; In a time, wherein the violence of our Enemies could not be reſtrained by any authority, after you had conducted, or accompanied the Armie that is incam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped againſt our brethren before the Towne of S. Iohn D'angely: if (as wee haue beene aſſured) you your ſelfe in perſon went to view the place, and vſed all the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience &amp; dexterity that God hath giuen you in Armes, to make the ſiege, and the meanes to take it more eaſie; what ſubiect haue not wee to complaine againſt you, who in ſtead of being ſicke for <hi>Ioſephes</hi> affliction, feare not to be the greateſt inſtrument of his murthering: Is it poſſible, that you cannot apprehend the ruine of ſo flouriſhing a Church, that God hath here gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and that you are not moued at the deſtruction that men ſeeke to bring vpon Monſieur <hi>De Sobize,</hi> and vpon ſo many braue Gentlemen, that haue beene the firſt that preſented themſelues in the mouth of the breach, that is made in the Citie of <hi>Dauid?</hi> that coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly labour to repaire the ſame, at this day in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wholly hindering that courſe of the deſtruction al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready begun in our Churches, and proiected againſt all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5934:6"/>of them. The knowledge that God hath giuen you of his holy name, bindeth you to employ that authority, whereunto hee hath aduanced you, and all the graces that hee hath imparted vnto you, and beſtowed vpon you, to the maintainance of his Church; and will you imploy them in the deſtruction thereof? Piety requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that you ſhould procure all good, and liberty vnto thoſe that make profeſſion of Religion, and will you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue and allow of their deſolation? Chriſtian charity can hardly endure without watry eyes, that wee ſhould ſee one man onely put to death: and can you with a ſmooth and ſmiling countenance, behold and ſee the butcherie and cruell ſlaughter of ſo many of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? What reputation can they get or procure vnto themſelues that fight againſt that Goſpell, whereof they make profeſſion? What fidelity may our Prince expect from them, that being not faithfull vnto God, abandon the maintainance of his cauſe? And from whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes this great diſtaſte of vs at this day, but only from this, that there are ſome men, (and thoſe of greateſt qualities) that giue themſelues to affect the Religion, as long, and no longer, then that it ſerueth their turnes to aduance them vnto dignities, and to encreaſe their riches? Is it not eaſie to be iudged, that if couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ambition, be a meanes to make them diſloyall vnto God, and to diſpiſe and neglect their owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the ſame vices will eaſily draw them on to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity towards their Prince, and to the diſpiſing of their owne honours? Was it a ſmall matter in your ſight, to ſee diuers Miniſters driuen away from their dwelling places, the exerciſe of Religion baniſhed out of thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> places, where it was eſtabliſhed, and the inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manities,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5934:6"/>which haue bin impiouſly vſed, within theſe few yeares vpon the dead bodies of the faithfull, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in all places of this Realme, The burnings and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of diuers of our Churches, the many ſeditions, and ſpecially that, laſt made in the Citie of Touers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the entier deſolation of thoſe of Bearn, haue they not touched nor mooued your ſoule with a Chriſtian compaſſion, and a iuſt apprehenſion, in ſhort time to behold and ſee thoſe horrible cruelties executed vpon vs and our children, that after the like proceedings were at other times executed vpon our fathers, and that after (as at this day) they had bin deceiued, by words of peace and quietneſſe? Certainely, my Lord, if you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that you hold that honor which you at this preſent enioy, from the bleſſings that God hath giuen vnto your armes, then when you employed them for the defence of his Church, you ought alſo to belieue, that if now, when you draw neere vnto the end of your dayes, it is time to crowne your workes, with moſt iuſt and Chriſtian actions, you become an enemie vnto, and procure the ruine of thoſe that with you make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truth of the Goſpell, he will be angry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, and will couer your face with ſhame and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie, you ſhall expoſe your ſelfe to be diſpiſed of all men, and made a laughter vnto thoſe namely that haue made vſe of you, to execute their wicked intents, and bring that curſe vpon your head, which he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth againſt thoſe that curſe his people, and thoſe moſt fearefull iudgements, which in his wrath, he ſheweth vpon thoſe, that riſe vp againſt, and withſtand the Kingdome of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt: all maner of the deaths of thoſe whom God loueth, are precious in his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5934:7"/>ſight; but he will require their blood at the hands of thoſe, that ſhall vniuſtly ſhed the ſame, he that toucheth them, toucheth the apple of his eye, and you are not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant thereof: With what conſcience then can you continue and remaine among our enemies, that abuſe the affections and conſcience of the King, for ours and the ſtates vtter ruine, giue counſell for the deſtruction of Townes, wherein the holy name of God is purely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoaked, and participate in the forcible action that are done againſt them? would you thruſt your ſword into the breſts of your owne brethren, and bath your hands in the blood of thoſe whom God hath redeemed by the blood of his deare Sonne Ieſus Chriſt? No my Lord, rather in the name of God, if there be any care of his Church, yet reſting in you, if there be any charity in your heart towards thoſe that are his members, and which is more, if you deſire not to bring vpon you and yours, the wrath and vengance of God (for we are bound by the duty of our Offices and the diſcharge of our conſciences to ſpeake in this maner vnto you) be mooued to compaſſion vpon the pittifull dealing which at this day is vſed againſt the faithfull, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the deceits and impoſtures of our enemies, note the violent courſes they vſe againſt your brethren, and with a prudent foreſight apprehending future miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, come out from the middle of them, leaſt you be enueloped among the plagues, that God will powre downe vpon the veſſels of his wrath, when he ſhall haue ceaſed the vſing of them, for the puniſhment of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Aide not them, that haue no other intent then to deſtroy vs, by making a deuiſion among vs: forſake not the members of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, but rather
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5934:7"/>ioyning with vs, bring the reſt of our brethren with you; who by your example, you haue withdrawne from vs; and vſe the meanes, to cauſe them alſo to come with you, who as yet are aſleepe, and reſt vnder the deceitfull aſſurances that are giuen them of ſome quietneſſe: to the end that being all, (according to our duties) moſt ſtricktly vnited together by the ſacred bands of pietie, peace, and charitie; we may effectually labour toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the publique Tranquility and quietneſſe of Gods houſe: And ſeeing that there is no other meanes left vnto vs, we employ a iuſt and couragious defence, which being bleſſed by God, ſtayeth the violent courſes of thoſe that perſecute vs, deliuereth the Towne of S. <hi>Iohn D'Angely</hi> from their hands, and preſerueth all the reſt: ſhall not ſo many perſons of good quality who acknowledging the vnfaithfulneſſe and the intents of our enemies, conſecrate their blood, to empeach the deſtruction of the faithfull, prouoake you, to a holy iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, by their example? You haue heretofore bin a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant inſtrument in the hand of God, to defend his Church from oppreſſion: be the ſame againe, my Lord, at this day, and that the rather and ſtronglie, becauſe God hath giuen you many bleſſings in aboundance. And if you diſpiſing theſe exhortations, that we giue you, by the compaſſion of Chriſt, be ſtill in this time, and faile in the ſuccours which you owe vnto all good men, God will not ceaſe to raiſe vp, peace and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance by other meanes, vnto his children. But it is to be ſeared, that he will reuenge, the diſſipation that you ſhall make of your brethren, vpon you and yours. We beſeech Almighty God, with all our hearts, to touch your heart by his holy Spirit, to inſpire you with God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5934:8"/>and godly connſell, to doe that which we require of you according to his will, and that receiuing you into his protection, he will take pitty vpon his Church, ſend peace vnto this State, and tranquility and ſecurity to thoſe troupes that he hath aſſembled therein. We reſt, my Lord, Your moſt humble and moſt affectioned ſeruants, the Deputies of the reformed Churches of France, and the Soueraignety of Bearn aſſembled in Rochell:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Beſſay.</hi> Preſident.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roſſell.</hi> Lieutenant.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Guerin.</hi> Secretarie.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>de la Por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e.</hi> Secretarie.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>In Rochell</hi> 
                  <date>the 12. <hi>of Iune.</hi> 1621.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5934:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
